[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the Sutta, Girimananda Sutta again, and one of the perceptions that need to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the perception of dispassion?
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's also the perception of cessation, but it's said in the same way, it's described the same way, dispassion and cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here Bhikkhu, having gone into
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no craving, dispassion, nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this type of perception can only start being developed after many others have been developed to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something that you can... it's also... it seems like more of a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, it's the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dispassion is a result that then, at some point,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when your mind has sufficiently developed, you recognize that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize this passion as a direct result, as a phenomenon that's the result of all previous efforts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you can single that phenomenon out and, like, amplify it, so to speak, emphasize it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you kind of develop these perceptions by recognizing them for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will not be able to recognize the phenomenon of dispassion, unless everything else that's been leading to dispassion has been developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be acting passionately, thinking about dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll just read another sutta which seems to relate in the Middle Length Discourse number 14.
[SPEAKER_00]: A person named Mahanāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's speaking to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, For a long time, sir, I have understood your teaching like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Greed, hatred and delusion are corruptions of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Despite understanding that sometimes my mind is occupied by thoughts of greed, hate and delusion,
[SPEAKER_00]: I wonder what qualities remain in me that I have such thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha replies, there is a quality that remains in you that makes you have such thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: For if you had given up that quality, you would not still be living at home and enjoying sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because you haven't given up that quality, you are still living at home and enjoying sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and stress.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when they do achieve their joy and pleasure, or something more peaceful than that, they will not return to sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: So long as they do not achieve the joy and pleasure that are apart from sensual pleasures and unbeneficial qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first thing to mention there is, people can sort of conclude on the basis of that paragraph that, aha!
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here I am, attracted to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me now find pleasure different to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will take my mind away from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let me experience the jhāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you read other suttas, though, the Buddha says that the only way to experience jhāna pleasure is to completely abandon sensual pleasure beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, I can't remember, I think in Siddhan Gautama Rinpoche, he said that one can experience jhāna, that develop jhāna, that abide in the first jhāna, without having thoroughly understood the gratification, danger, and the escape from sensuality, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's impossible to have jhāna, to develop jhāna, to abide in jhāna, to cultivate jhāna, unless you have fully seen, developed the danger of sensuality, that perception, and fully lost interest in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you develop the jhāna, and if that's done sufficiently enough, let's say like that, the mind will lose even any underlying inclination to return to sensuality, if it becomes careless and falls off from jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that quality needs to be developed, but the only way to develop it, that's like almost like a catch-22.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to develop it is to first see the danger in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already how you develop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the quality that Mahānāma needs to see, really, most acutely, is the danger in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will then result in the quality of pleasure different to sensuality, that then he can cultivate and not return to sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are abandoning sensual pleasures, withdrawing from them,
[SPEAKER_00]: And over time, you don't automatically get jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do feel joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, because you're free from danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the danger of sensuality does not apply to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get the joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you would get the joy if you just escaped a death trap or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not have some other pleasure now, but you certainly have pleasure of freedom from a death trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not a small thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's important to recognize that
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't replace sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't knock it out as a peg with another pleasure that's not sensual, because that principle is always sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if people try to get the jhānas, and hoping that that will free them from sensuality, that will be the sensual meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way to get jhānas, to discover direction of jhāna, and the wholesome pleasure that's not the sensual one,
[SPEAKER_01]: is to fully see the danger of sensuality, contemplate the danger, contemplate the peril of the trap, and all the hunter similes, and everything else, until you, like, absolutely mind becomes incapable of activating towards that type of pleasure, because of the fear of the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we compare that to having a mental intent, eh... directed everywhere else, except to the charcoal pit, where the... where two strong men are dragging it towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you should regard sensuality, like a charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead, do you think that man that's about to be thrown in a charcoal pit, do you think even like a tiny, like, sort of, any molecule of his being, would he be able to think, okay, no, I'll go to the charcoal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: His intention would want to be everywhere else but there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the intention that must be cultivated towards sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's sufficiently developed
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already a form of, you know, a substantial freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: That then, if you dwell secluded like that for a while, that's then the pleasure of seclusion, that's developed beforehand, that then is accompanied later on by jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, but so that's... that pleasure of withdrawal, that pleasure of seclusion, is a pleasure which, you know, which one can experience and... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a pleasure of relief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Relief from the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, but it's basically, it's prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what he says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having been secluded from centrality, he experiences the pleasure on account of that seclusion from centrality, and then he enters and abides in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pleasure in jhāna is the pleasure of seclusion from centrality, not the pleasure of a mystical experience of jhānic absorption or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the pleasure of safety, the relief of safety, that then, if you dwell long enough, your mind will be established in correct thinking and pondering, there will not be spilling out into domain that doesn't pertain to you, the clarity will be established, the mindfulness will be unwavering, and that's the jhāna, on the basis of that pleasure of seeing the danger in sensuality and refusing to go there anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any person
[SPEAKER_00]: restrains their senses, sustaining that wild animal, and it calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is a experience of calmness on account of that, which is peaceful, which is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... that comes from not being wild, not letting this animal run wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that pleasure is higher than sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because that animal is now tamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's subtler.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's subtler.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's higher, but it's more refined, that pleasure of taming the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more refined.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even, you know, so it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's harder to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it takes cultivating, and it takes getting used to, and it takes time to start seeing the true value of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might see the value of it when you go really far with, you know, letting the wild animal run loose, and then you see the value of peace generated by that kind of wild animal you created.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, you want to see the value of peace, even if you don't let the animal run wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, there's no contrast.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to not need the contrast.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the value of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to always see the value of peace, regardless of the contrast or the absence of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, but so, even if someone's been doing that for a long time, taming that animal, let the animals tame, and they're not doing anything unwholesome, and they haven't been wild for one year, two years,
[SPEAKER_00]: They can recognize that they are quite calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes, but they still might be attracted to centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if their environment would change, or become more challenging, or something, I don't know, the mind might revert back to, you know, the pleasure, in that it has not fully seen the drawbacks of, and the danger in, the pleasure of centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, he had the right view there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he asked that question, he said, you know, a noble disciple who clearly understood, yet sometimes he still remains attracted to this sensuality and the mind gets clouded with sensual desire and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's because you have not thoroughly developed yourself in regard to, as the Buddha says, your own body, through seeing the danger of that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the body presents you with the prospect of physical pleasure, through its senses, your mind is not developed to withstand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you develop it, like that mind, that withstanding, by contemplating the danger of that prospect, and enduring the danger of the prospect, enduring the pull and the pain of saying no to it, and not acting out of it, and then contemplating the danger, and when the danger is absent, think like valuing the peace and the absence of danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing that escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be... it needs to be taken as if your life depends on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you don't take it like that burning charcoal pit, the mind will not be, you know... well, it won't turn away from it sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the danger will not become apparent in its entirety.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might see the drawbacks, you know, as an afterthought.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might keep you in check.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see the presence of the prospect of pleasure is the presence of peril in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not two seconds later, or a millisecond later, or tomorrow, or if... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of that possibility is... means the other side of that same coin is the peril.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, there is no touching it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no even for a second wanting the charcoal burning pit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's important to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to see the drawbacks of sensuality correctly, they must not be seen as the future results of it, which they also are.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might start like that, but you need to see it as the immediate presence of danger with the immediate presence of possibility of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like two sides of the same coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when the danger is apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was saying about the relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might experience the relief that comes from
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you shouldn't be complacent, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you experience the relief, great, and then see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I still, like, will I in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could I in the future be still attracted to sensual pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, okay, let's wait and see.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the meantime, I just have to be very careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Value your relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Value the relief, protect
[SPEAKER_00]: And another sutta that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it might be the same one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, yeah, I think it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha asks Mahānāma again.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the king, Bimbisara, is the king endowed with those five cores of sensual pleasures, capable of experiencing perfect happiness and joy for
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one who has something, who needs to do something in order to get the pleasure, or the one who doesn't need to do anything in order to abide in pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who's better off?
[SPEAKER_01]: The one who doesn't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation of activities.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the person going after sensual objects, sensual pleasures, has to do all these activities to maintain it, to get it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they can have loads of money, access, loads of access to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet... Well, as great as that pleasure might be, it always depends on the activity, depends on needing to do, depends on duty and burden and pressure to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the one that doesn't need sensual objects and sensual pleasures,
[SPEAKER_00]: He gets a higher pleasure, a more refined pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that he doesn't need to feed, maintain, and it's not pressured by.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it involves that non-involvement with those unwholesome activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result of the non-involvement with the unwholesome activities, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what about it as an encouragement?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, there's that, like that one sutta where the Buddha takes, he shows one monk, I think, Nanda, his name was, and he takes him to these heavenly realms, it says, and he shows Nanda these celestial nymphs, or whatever, that are very attractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, which is, you know, which is better?
[SPEAKER_00]: The
[SPEAKER_00]: those women on earth that you are attracted to, all these celestial beings, and yeah, and then he said, if you restrain from, if you remain celibate, give up sensual pleasures of worldly kind, you'll get rewarded in heaven with these
[SPEAKER_00]: You went quite far, became a noble disciple and finished the job.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you never got those heavenly pleasures, I don't think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the question?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that... so, the encouragement, like, well, here is a better pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, none of that encouragement pertains to the pleasures that you know of this world, which are entirely central pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, if you need an encouragement of heavenly rewards,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still within sensuality, but it's not within this sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will at least remain celibate and withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha did say that perfect celibacy, basically, is not just being celibate in this life, but not wanting rewards of heaven.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the perfect celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he wasn't perfect and that's why he started feeling ashamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why he became a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of shame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I said, oh, he's only doing this for a heavenly place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other monks started saying, well, what kind of monk this is?
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just a monk because he wants to be rewarded with nims in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he started feeling very ashamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he made the effort and became a noble disciple and abandoned sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even as an encouragement, it didn't really make him abandon sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the encouragement that at least kind of enabled him to not give up the holy life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, as a last resort, which he was going to do, yeah, he went to the Buddha to say he's going to go back.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a servant girl, or whatever else was in the Sutta mentioned there, that's waiting for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, well, okay, you know, if you don't go back, these are the pleasures that wait for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, okay, so I'll stay because I want the nims in the next life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he didn't become a noble disciple on account of that, but he stayed a monk on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he felt ashamed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And dejected when he heard what other monks are saying and then sort of made the effort and became resolute and abandoned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want jhānas in this life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need to abandon principle of sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's this or the next heaven, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to not want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see the peril of it infinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not replace it, not delay it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through and through.
[SPEAKER_01]: Must be not wanted anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that comes from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as a person expects not wanting to come out of circumstances, out of results, out of techniques or something, it's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can only come out of wisdom that you developed for yourself, within yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, tenacity, virtue, guarding the senses and pondering on the dangers of those pleasures, thoroughly and thoroughly and thoroughly, until the dangers are seen immediately in the prospect of the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even a second after.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel the threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: The threat is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poisonous drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: See?
[SPEAKER_01]: You drink it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poison is in that agreeable drink.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, eh, here is the poison after when you drink that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the drink is the poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the prospect of that pleasure is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you need to see that for yourself.